בוקר טוב. Boker tov.
So, let's see. Today's דף Daf is פ"ב, Pei Bet, eighty-two. And
where do we pick up? We pick up three lines down from
the top of the דף. Daf. אמר ליה. Amar Lei. So we
are wrapping up this פרק perek which deals with the various sizes
of objects for carrying, but the recent discussion had been about stones
and pieces of pottery and using them to wipe yourself and that
חז"ל Chazal were willing to override מוקצה muktzeh for the sake of
כבוד הבריות. kevod habriyot. Within that context we continue now, three lines
from the top, פ"ב עמוד א'. Pei Bet Amud Aleph. אמר ליה
רב הונא לרבה בריה. Amar Lei Rav Huna Le-Rabba Brei. So רב
הונא Rav Huna said to רבה Rabba his son: "מאי טעמא לא
שכיחת קמיה דרב חסדא? Mai Tama Lo Shachichat Kammei De-Rav Chisda? Why
are you not, why do you not frequent in the presence of
רב חסדא? Rav Chisda? דמחדדן שמעתא, De-Mechadedin Shemaata, that he is
teaching is very sharp, you know, you could be learning a lot
from him. Why are you not going there to learn from him?"
אמר ליה, Amar Lei, "מאי איזיל לגביה? Mai Izil Ligebei? Why should
I go to him?
דכי אזיל לגביה מותיב לי במילי דעלמא, De-Ki Azil Ligebei, Mostiv Li
Be-Milei De-Alma, and teaches me regarding like everyday matters, mundane issues, not
תורה." Torah.
What does this mean? So this is like רבקה Rivka was complaining
about yesterday, he talks to me about medicine, not about תורה. Torah.
אמר
לי, Amar Li, he says to me, "מאן דעייל לבי כסא, Man
De-Ayil Le-Ve Kisei, when you go to the bathroom, a person who
goes to the bathroom, לא ליתיב בהדי, Lo Leisiv Be-Hadi, don't sit
down like quickly, suddenly.
ולא ליטרח טפי, Ve-Lo Litrach Tfei, and don't exert yourself too much,
you know, try to push yourself too much. דהאי כרכשתא אתלת שיני
יתיב,
De-Hai Karkashta Atlas Shina
Yasiv, because the rectum sits on three teeth, like on three muscles
or whatever. There are three things that maybe it's like the lower
intestine or whatever, you know, is somehow connected to various three muscles
in the body. Who knows?
אתלת יתיב. Atlas Yasiv.
No, they're, they're muscles that support the pelvis. Okay. There's three of
them? Huh? There's three of them?
All right, whatever. Anyway, okay. So there are muscles that support the
pelvis or whatever.
דילמא משתמטא שינא דכרכשתא ואתי לידי סכנה, Dilma Mishtamta Shina De-Karkashta Ve-Ati
Lidei Sakana, and if you push yourself too hard or if you
sit down too quickly, then one of them will sort of move,
dislocate, and you'll become and you'll endanger yourself. So I need to
go to a rabbi to tell me that? So אמר ליה, Amar
Lei, "הוא עסיק בחיי דבריאתא, Hu Asik Be-Chayei De-Briyata, he is concerning
himself with the life of God's creatures. ואת אמרת במילי דעלמא? Ve-At
Amrat Be-Milei De-Alma? And you say it's a mundane matter?" I mean
he's concerned about people's
health. כל שכן זיל לגביה, Kol Sheken Zil Ligebei, how much more
so should you go by him that you should learn this critical
thing about things that are necessary for your well-being. Okay. So that
was a little bit of a connecting obviously to issues around going
to the bathroom and other issues we mentioned the other day about
concerns about health and so on. All right, so. What, did he
go? What, it doesn't say, right, it doesn't say whether he listened
to his father or not. And also doesn't say whether the rabbi
was supposed to have had special knowledge of these, but it's still
saying it's a very important thing to be concerned about. Okay. היו
לפניו צרור וחרס. Hayu Lefanav Tzror Ve-Cheres. Now back to הלכה, halacha,
as it relates to this. So, he has, you can choose between
a rock and a piece of pottery. And presumably it's שבת. Shabbos.
So if you remember yesterday, one of the points was don't try
to be so פרום frum and get the pottery which is less
מוקצה muktzeh if the pottery is more possibly dangerous to you because
it'll either scratch or make you susceptible to witchcraft. So even on
שבת Shabbos take the rock, take the thing that is safer. So,
just lost connection?
Something.
All right, anyway, that was weird. Okay. Anyway. Okay. So take the
rock which is safer. רב הונא אמר, Rav Huna Amar, so what
do you do? So רב הונא אמר, Rav Huna Amar, "מקנח בצרור
ואין מקנח בחרס." Mekaneach Be-Tzror Ve-Ein Mekaneach Be-Cheres. So רב הונא Rav
Huna says use the rock and don't use the pottery for the
reason we said yesterday. It's either more abrasive or because of witchcraft
and therefore fine, use the rock, don't worry yourself about מוקצה. muktzeh.
רב חסדא אמר, Rav Chisda Amar, רב חסדא Rav Chisda says, "מקנח
בחרס ואין מקנח בצרור." Mekaneach Be-Cheres Ve-Ein Mekaneach Be-Tzror. No, use the,
so he's taking the firmer approach which we rejected yesterday, quote unquote
firmer, but one that's sort of less safety concerned, and use the
pottery which is less of a מוקצה muktzeh issue and don't use
the rock. So מיתיבי, Meiseivei, I'll ask you on this. We have
a ברייתא: Braisa: "היו לפניו צרור וחרס מקנח בחרס ואין מקנח בצרור."
Hayu Lefanav Tzror Ve-Cheres, Mekaneach Be-Cheres Ve-Ein Mekaneach Be-Tzror.
It's like רב חסדא Rav Chisda says, not like רב הונא, Rav
Huna, not like we said yesterday. Use the pottery, don't use the
rock. תיובתא דרב הונא, Tiyuvta De-Rav Huna, that's a contradiction to רב
הונא. Rav Huna. So תרגמה רפרם בר פפא קמיה דרב חסדא, Targeima
Rafram Bar Pappa Kammei De-Rav Chisda, so רפרם בר פפא Rafram Bar
Pappa interpreted it in the presence
of
רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, אליבא דרב הונא, Aliba De-Rav Huna, according to
רב הונא, Rav Huna, באוגני כלים. Be-Ugnei Keilim. That's talking about like
it's a handle of a vessel. If you think about like a
handle, right, it's not sharp, it's nice and smooth and it's narrow.
So that could be used effectively
without endangering yourself. So that's a legitimate alternative or maybe a better
alternative to a
rock,
right?
Yes, did they reject the idea that the problem with the earthenware
shard is that it'll pull hairs out?
You mean the specific Shabbat issue? Yeah, they seem not to be
concerned about it because of what it said yesterday about דבר שאינו
מתכוין davar she'eino mitkaven that you're not intending and it's not a
פסיק רישא psik reisha and so yeah, they seem unconcerned with that
at this stage. Okay, so we're still not done, we're getting there
though.
Now you can choose between a rock and grass. And presumably it's
Shabbat. So we know the rock has the מוקצה muktzah problem, what
problem does the grass have? So it could be תולש, toleish, of
course then how could we're going to see there's some opinions that
you use the grass, how could anybody think you use the grass
if it's תולש? toleish? So it might be Rashi says that you
use the grass while it's still attached.
So you actually you know wipe yourself on it if it's long
grass without pulling it out and it wouldn't really be like a
מוקצה muktzah issue because you're not really moving it. It raises interesting
questions about מוקצה, muktzah, you know, if you like if you move
something and it remains rooted in one place and you move it
back and forth is that מוקצה? muktzah? If you haven't moved it
from its place? But that's what one possibility Rashi suggests is that
you leave it attached and it's not מוקצה muktzah because you're not
really moving it from its place and it's what?
The grass is it just grass?
He has some tall grass, you use it without moving without pulling
up the grass. Okay, so then it's less of a מוקצה muktzah
concern but it's more of a concern you might come to pull
up the grass. The other possibility is not related to Shabbat at
all but it's that grass could scratch and it's also flammable and
we're going to see in a minute that there's concerns around using
flammable toilet paper either for witchcraft concerns or other types of concerns.
So you have to choose now, I guess this is a variation
of a rock and a hard
place, between a rock and pottery, between rock and grass. What are
you going to use? So רב חסדא ורב המנונא, Rav Chisda veRav
Hamnuna, so it's a debate between רב חסדא ורב המנונא. Rav Chisda
veRav Hamnuna. חד אמר מקנח בצר ואין מקנח בעשבים, chad amar meka'neach
betzor ve'ein meka'neach ba'asavim,
one says you use the rock and you don't use grass, וחד
אמר מקנח בעשבים ואין מקנח בצר, vechad amar meka'neach ba'asavim ve'ein meka'neach
betzor, you'd rather use the grass than the rock, either because the
rock is more of a מוקצה muktzah issue.
מתיבי, meitivei, I'll ask you a ברייתא, braita, המקנח בדבר שהאור שולט
בו שיניו התחתונות נושרות, hameka'neach bedavar sheha'or sholet bo shinav hatachtonot noshrot,
if you wipe yourself with something that is flammable, your you know
your teeth below presumably like you know your no no no, but
it means the it means the you know the things within inside
your inside your anus, the various whatever, I don't even know the
medical term, but what? What did you say? Sphincter? Something like that.
What what did you say?
Anyway,
I don't think that their knowledge of
anatomy—well, I know, but I still think they had some sense of
what they were describing, I mean they weren't describing stuff that was
like you know stuff that was very close to the surface, I
think it means whatever, the parts that you know that cause it
to to it might be the sphincter, I mean the stuff that
causes it to close and open anyway, the rough you know the
stuff that's like a little rigid inside anyway, it's something inside of
your you know there falls out. So now what's the reason? Is
it because it's just abrasive? Then why does it have to do
with being related to flammable?
Flammable and abrasive are not necessarily the same category. So it does
seem from other places that it's a concern about like I said
it makes you susceptible to witchcraft. Interestingly, תוספות Tosafot says that
where's תוספות? Tosafot?
One minute,
תוספות Tosafot quotes
ירושלמי. Yerushalmi.
No, where's the תוספות? Tosafot? No, previous page, thank you, where where
is the תוספות? Tosafot? Anyway, somebody here was quoting ירושלמי Yerushalmi that
says the exact opposite of the בבלי, Bavli, that says that דווקא
davka you should use something that's flammable and not something that's not
flammable. Yeah, okay, I'll find it in a minute. What?
That's what it says here in the note,
the ירושלמי.
Yerushalmi. Or הריטב"א haRitva says, yeah, one of the מפרשים mefarshim points
out the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says the opposite. Okay, it's not תוספות. Tosafot.
But anyway, wait, let's see what the גמרא Gemara says, hold on.
So anyway, so don't use flammable things, obviously it'll be very dangerous.
So what do you do? So how can somebody say that you
should use the grass? So the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא הא
בלחים הא ביבשים. lo kashya, ha belachim ha biyevashim. No, it's not
difficult, the difference is whether it's moist or whether it's dry. If
it's dry then it's flammable and then that's a problem, and if
it's moist then it is not flammable or not so flammable and
therefore it is not a problem. Yes, Charlie, yeah, but right, but
so the
ArtScroll says the
quotes the ערוך השולחן Aruch Hashulchan is saying the practice of witchcraft
today is virtually unknown, which was true when the ערוך השולחן Aruch
Hashulchan was written but that's not true today.
You know what, let's say effective witchcraft, okay? So alright anyway, so
now the גמרא Gemara says right, I mean obviously if you took
this if you applied this להלכה lehalacha it means you couldn't use
toilet paper. So anyway. Okay, so anyway, so that's the answer. So
when we're saying you can do it according to those that say
you could, it's when it's moist. הניצרך לפנות ואינו נפנה, Hanitzrach lepanot
ve'eino nifneh,
now if you have to relieve yourself and you do not, רב
חסדא ורבינא Rav Chisda veRavina so they debate whether what's the effect
of this. חד אמר רוח רעה שולטת בו, Chad amar ruach ra
sholeteit bo, you get bad breath, וחד אמר רוח זוהמא שולטת בו,
vechad amar ruach zu'ama sholeteit bo, you get general body odor, your
entire body tends to stink. תניא כמאן דאמר
רוח זוהמא שולטת בו, Tanya keman de'amar ruach zu'ama sholeteit bo, we
taught like the latter opinion, דתניא detanya we taught in a ברייתא,
baraita, הניצרך לנקביו hanitzrach lenekavav if somebody needs to go to the
bathroom ואוכל ve'ochel and you eat even though you right need to,
you know, relieve yourself.
So what's the point? You're eating and you got food you got
to get rid of right now. So דומה לתנור שהסיקוהו על גבי
אפרו, domeh letannur shehisikuo al gabei efro, it's like lighting up an
oven over its ashes, right? What happens? You burn an oven, you
after it's been burned you have all these ashes. So it's if
you want to make a new fire, put in new fuel, you
clean out the residue of the old fuel, you clean out the
ashes. So you've eaten, you've consumed the food, before you put in
new food, you should be cleaning out the waste of the old
food before you burn the new food. And when you it's like
you are trying to light an oven that already has a big
pile of ashes, which obviously is going to be smelly and inefficient.
And therefore what so what's the effect of that? וזו היא תחלת
רוח זוהמא, Vezu hi techilat ruach zu'ama, and
that leads this the beginning of a stench, of a body odor.
So there you see that's the effect of eating when you have
to go to the bathroom. הוצרך לפנות ואינו יכול לפנות, Hutzrach lepanot
ve'eino yachol lepanot, now let's say you have to relieve yourself and
you're not able to, right, exactly. What's the solution? So
they didn't have laxatives. So אמר רב חסדא יעמוד וישב יעמוד וישב.
amar Rav Chisda ya'amod veyeshev ya'amod veyeshev. Stand
right, well
not calisthenics, that's not what they're saying. Saying you stand and you
sit, you stand and you sit, so that sort of, you know,
moving it's not it's no, they're not talking about calisthenics. They're talking
about you're trying to go to the bathroom and it's not working,
you stand up for a little bit, then you sit back down
and somehow that gets you your body to, you know, it makes
it more easy for you to relieve yourself. What?
It moves the muscle on top of your intestine to move your
intestine.
Is that what it does? Okay, there you go. So it moves
the so so so moves the so according to Sally, it moves
the muscles on top of your intestines and therefore thereby moving your
intestines and thereby okay fine. Would it be the same if you
basically just tried to like move you know with your hands, move
around in your stomach area?
It's just more effective if you use your
your whole body's muscle, your whole okay. So therefore okay, thank you.
So that's suggestion number one. רב אחא מדפתי אמר יסתלק לצדדין, Rav
Acha miDifti amar yistalek litzdadim, go try sitting somewhere else. You know,
if you're trying to go in this corner go you know this
is when they were going in the woods so it was like
go to another place in the woods. So משמע משנה מקום, mashmeh
misheneh makom, maybe,
or maybe it has it's similar to this except just I don't
know telling you to go to a different place. But I guess
it gets you standing up and moving and sitting down somewhere else
too.
Okay. רב המנונא אמר ימשמש בצרור באותו מקום, Rav Hamnuna amar yemashmesh
betzor be'oto makom, and this is what we saw before that the
use of the rock was not just to wipe yourself but also
to stimulate that area and to help to help get it to
and therefore so you use a rock to you know to rub
yourself in that area and you stimulate it and that's supposed to
help relieve yourself. Sally, does that work? It's supposed to work. A
suppository is when you stick something in, right? What? No, I think
it means that I understood it meant that you sort of stimulate
the outside, the opening, not actually sticking something. But I thought a
suppository wasn't just anything in, I thought it was something that actually
had some doesn't a suppository have some type of a chemical or
whatever that has that effect? This is a rock. So I thought
it had to do with more like just stimulating the nerve endings
or something.
Like babies, I mean a lot of the time you take their
temperature and you know.
So there you go. Right, okay. Alright. So
רבנן אמרי יסיח דעתו rabanan amri yassiach da'ato and the Rabbis say
distract yourself. Think about something else. So so you so that's that's
the tradition about you having good reading material in the bathroom. So
אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי, amar leh Rav Acha
berei deRava leRav Ashi, so רב אחא Rav Acha the son of
of of רב אחא Rav Acha said I'm sorry רב אחא Rav
Acha the son of רבא Rava said to רב אשי, Rav Ashi,
כל שכן דכי מסיח דעתו לא מפני, kol sheken dechi masiach da'ato
lo mafni, he thinks it'll be counterproductive if you're thinking about something
else, certainly it'll you won't be able to relieve yourself. אמר ליה
amar leh so he said no, מסיח דעתו מדברים אחרים, masiach da'ato
midvarim acherim, no, to remove your attention from other things, completely focus
on this. All right, so I don't know. It could be that
the גמרא Gemara really meant it before, like you know if you're
too focused it won't be that effective either. Anyway, but here are
saying the opposite. Okay. אמר רב ירמיה מדפתי לדידי חזי לי ההוא
טייעא, Amar Rav Yirmiyah miDifti ledidi chazi li hahu taya, I saw
a an Arab like a nomad, דקם ויתיב קם ויתיב, dekum veyativ
kum veyativ, that when he would have to go to the bathroom
he would stand up and sit, stand and sit, עד דשפיך כקדרה,
ad deshaphich kekedeira, until he spilled out like a like a you
know like a pot, like it just was extremely helpful for him
in order to relieve yourself. Okay. תנו רבנן Tanu rabanan let's not
let's not get in among in in this in this context. הנכנס
לסעודת קבע, Hanichnas lise'udat keva, if you're going to a a like
a formal dinner, a fixed dinner meaning that it's going to be
first of all maybe you want to eat a lot, number two
is as רש"י Rashi says it's going to be embarrassing if you
have to. leave in the middle to excuse yourself to go to
the bathroom. So you want to take care of all of that
beforehand. So what do you do? יהלך Yahaleich י' פעמים yud pe'amim
של shel ארבע ארבע אמות, arba arba amot, either you take ten
short walks of four אמות amot each which is six feet, but
you know like not so you go six feet, you sit down,
you stand up, you go six feet, you sit down. So I
guess that's a lot of the standing and sitting, standing and sitting
that takes place and walking that moves stuff around. ואמרי לה, V'amri
lei, and some say ארבע פעמים של עשר עשר אמות, arba pe'amim
shel eser eser amot, or some say four walks of ten אמות
amot each ונפנה, venifneh, and then you go to the bathroom ונכנס,
venichnas, and then you come in
וישב במקומו, veyashev bimkomo, sit at your meal in the dinner and
you will not have to leave in the middle. And רש"י Rashi
by the way says
that every time you're sitting down, you're checking yourself to see if
you can relieve yourself, but the גמרא Gemara itself just meant that
you try these ten times or four times and then you go
to try to relieve yourself. Who says
he sits down on this? It doesn't, but what does it mean
ten walks times four or four walks times ten? If you're just
doing it straight, it might have said you walk forty אמות. amot.
Maybe, maybe you just pause, could be. Or
right out the door. Right, right. Just went for a walk. Exactly.
All right. Now, moving on, ending this פרק perek about the sizes
of things that you carry. Isn't there that famous book, I think
I read it, 'The Things They Carried', right? Who's that by, that
book about the Vietnam War? Nobody knows this book? It's a great
book on the Vietnam War, 'The Things They Carried'. Anyway, okay, fine.
So that's got to be some פירוש pirush there anyway. So, last
משנה Mishnah of the פרק. perek. חרס כדי ליתן בין פצים לחבירו.
Cheres kedei litein bein patzim lachaveiro. So if you have little pieces
of pottery, interestingly, not the size to wipe yourself, the minimum size
for little pieces of pottery is to put between like beams of
wood, like you know you have like the laying beams of wood
and you've got and they've got little gaps, so it's going to
cause it to move and to bend, so you want like little
pieces of pottery to like, you know, to just to fill the
gaps. So those types of sizes. דברי רבי יהודה. Divrei Rabbi Yehuda.
That's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says. רבי מאיר אומר כדי לחתות
בו את האור, Rabbi Meir omer kedei lachtot bo et ha'or, in
order to use to scrape the fire, you know, you use to
move around pieces of wood or charcoal in the fire, you take
a little piece of pottery as a poker. רבי יוסי אומר כדי
לקבל בו רביעית, Rabbi Yossi omer kedei lekabel bo revi'it, in order
to use something that's big enough to hold a רביעית revi'it of
liquid. So that has to really be a particular shape of pottery,
right? It has to be curved and it's got to be it's
not just a flat piece of pottery. So that's obviously a not
only larger but also much more limiting. אמר רבי מאיר, Amar Rabbi
Meir, אף על פי שאין ראיה לדבר זכר לדבר. af al pi
she'ein raya ladavar zecher ladavar. Although there's no proof that the idea
of pottery being very functional thing is a good use of it
to scrape, you know, to sort of move around fire, there's a
there's a there's a sort of a, you know, a hint to
it based on a פסוק pasuk in נביאים. Nevi'im. So when we
quote from תורה, Torah, that's considered a ראיה. raya. When we quote
from the rest of נ"ך, Nach, that's a זכר. zecher. That hints
to the idea, it's not an absolute proof but it hints to
my position. What's the פסוק pasuk say? לא ימצא במכיתתו חרס לחתות
אש מיקוד. Lo yimatzei bimchitato cheres lachtot eish miyaked. There will not
be found when like it's shattered a even a piece of pottery
to to like to scrape, you know, to what's it called, not
scrape but stir the fire, you know, to stir a burning fire.
So this is in a קללה kelala in ישעיהו Yeshayahu about what's
going to happen to the people because you know they they abandon
God and they won't even find a piece of pottery to do
this small little thing. So you see that that's a classic use
of pottery. אמר ליה רבי יוסי, Amar lei Rabbi Yossi, רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yossi said back, משם ראיה, misham raya, that's a proof? How
about the end of the פסוק? pasuk? ולחשוף מים מגבא. Velachsof mayim
migeva. It says you also won't find pottery to draw water from
the, you know, from a from a pond or, you know, from
a from a hole. So you see that pottery is also used
to draw water. Okay. So איבעיא להו, Iba'ya lehu, they ask, שיעורא
דרבי מאיר נפיש או שיעורא דרבי יוסי נפיש? shi'ura d'Rabbi Meir nafish
o shi'ura d'Rabbi Yossi nafish? Which one is bigger, the one of
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir or the one of רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yossi?
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who says the stirring the fire, רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yossi says drawing the water. נסתברא שיעורא דרבי יוסי נפיש. Nistabra
shi'ura d'Rabbi Yossi nafish. It makes sense that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi's
is bigger. Obviously, you presumably need a bigger piece of pottery to
draw water than you do just to like, you know, stir the
fire. ומקרא, Umikra, but based on the פסוקים psukim that they quoted,
it sounds like שיעורא דרבי מאיר נפיש. shi'ura d'Rabbi Meir nafish. It
sounds like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir's is bigger. Why does it sound
like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir's is bigger from the פסוקים psukim they
quoted? דאי סלקא דעתך שיעורא דרבי יוסי נפיש, De'ei salka daitach shi'ura
d'Rabbi Yossi nafish, if רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi's is is bigger, so
לייתי ליה במנא זוטא והדר לייתי ליה במנא רבא? leitei lei bemana
zuta vehadar leitei lei bemana raba? So it doesn't make sense. First
it says you won't have a piece of pottery to stir the
fire. So if pottery if the pottery to stir fire was a
smaller size, which makes sense, then it would be saying you won't
have even a small piece of pottery to stir fire. And not
only that, you won't even have a big piece of pottery to
draw water. So obviously that doesn't make sense. You must be saying
first you don't have a big one, then not a small one.
So presumably from the פסוק, pasuk, it sounds like the stirring of
the fire is a bigger one. So all right, maybe. Anyway, so
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, no,
מתניתין נמי לחתות אש מקידה גדולה. matnitin nami lachtot eish mikida gedola.
Our משנה, Mishnah, it's interesting, he might just take the פסוקים, psukim,
but anyway he's now actually saying not just
So that's why we go from big to small, you are right
the פסוקים psukim sound like that and we're talking about a big
piece of pottery of course, you could say that's what the פסוקים
psukim are talking about, but that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is talking
even about a small piece of pottery for a small fire, yes.
Sense says the same thing. Okay.
You don't want to burn yourself, so right,
you need a big piece of pottery. Now it's also true by
the way that in biblical poetry, sometimes it is anti-climactic, meaning it
says the it's you know like it says I was thinking there's
the פסוק pasuk I remember reading this somewhere this you know where
this point that biblical poetry sometimes says the bigger point and then
goes back, like there's a פסוק pasuk what is it? ירוצו ולא
ייגעו ילכו ולא ייעפו Yarutzu velo yigau yelchu velo yi-afu I think
is that the פסוק? pasuk? So right, right, they'll run
and they won't be weary, and they'll walk and they won't tire.
You know? So first it would be the opposite, right? You walk
you are tired you run you won't weary. So sometimes actually biblical
poetry does go in the reverse, but interestingly the גמרא Gemara does
not assume that here. Anyway, okay. שרבי יוסי אומר משם ראיה She-Rabbi
Yossi omer misham ra'aya so רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says that's a
proof, you know, look at the end of the פסוק pasuk that
you also use it for drawing water. So שפיר קאמר ליה רבי
יוסי, Shapir ka'amar leh Rabbi Yossi, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi makes a
good point that you use it for drawing water so that you
should be the size, especially if we've now decided that's the smaller
size, so that should dictate, we should go by the stricter size
and the smaller size. So שפיר קאמר ליה רבי יוסי לרבי מאיר,
Shapir ka'amar leh Rabbi Yossi le-Rabbi Meir, he made a good point
to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would say
לא מיבעיא קאמר, Lo mibaya ka'amar, it goes without
saying. לא מיבעיא מידי דחשיב לאינש לא לישתכח ליה, Lo mibaya midi
de-chashiv le-inash lo lishtakach leh, it goes without saying that people won't
find something that, you know, that is very, you know, is very
important and very useful pottery to scrape, you know, to stir fire,
even that, you know, that won't be found, אלא אפילו מידי דלא
חשיב לאינש, ela afilu midi dela chashiv le-inash, even things that people
aren't, you know, that is not so important, you know, even like
a secondary use won't be available to them, לא לישתכח ליה lo
lishtakach leh they won't find it, so they won't find, they won't
find enough pottery to draw water, meaning they won't be able to
find the pottery to do, you know, the primary function that it
does, which is the more important function, that won't be available to
them, and even the secondary function of it will not be available
to them, but we're still will be saying that the stirring of
the fire is the primary function and that's why he defines it
by that. הדרן עלך המוציא יין, Hadran alach ha-motzi yayin, that is
the end of that פרק perek of המוציא יין. Ha-motzi yayin. As
I said, we are not yet done with carrying. And again, I
just say this multiple times, it is shocking how many chapters, besides
that we have a whole מסכת Masechet coming up devoted by carrying,
but the very first משנה Mishna is about carrying, right? Then you
had במה בהמה ובמה אשה, Bameh behemah u-vameh ishah, two chapters about
what animals and people can wear, and now we've had, you know,
the end of כלל גדול, Klal gadol, which is about the size
of things that you can carry, המוציא יין Ha-motzi yayin which is
the eighth, so when you think about it and you really think
about how like, why it really is bizarre, it's not just it
happens to be that this is where more material is to discuss,
because the only relevance for these minimum sizes is primarily about whether
you have to bring a חטאת chatas offering and you're not allowed
to carry even less than a minimum size. And nevertheless, the amount
of, I mean it could be to say דאורייתא, de-oraisa, דרבנן, de-rabanan,
certain קולות, kulot, but the fact that how much effort is devoted
to all of this. And then the ninth פרק, perek, which is
what we're coming up I'll tell you what it is in a
minute. But then we have the tenth פרק perek which is המצניע,
Ha-matznia, if you put stuff aside, remember when you put things aside
then it's even a smaller size. Then the eleventh פרק perek is
הזורק, Ha-zorek, which is about throwing things, also about carrying, right? And
it's not until we get to the end of the eleventh פרק
perek that we start talking about the other מלאכות. melachot. So there
really is about a third roughly of מסכת שבת Masechet Shabbos is
devoted to carrying. A third, and a whole מסכת ערובין. Masechet Eruvin.
So I really, you know, I really don't know the explanation for
that, but it is we're still not done with carrying, but we're
about to have a פרק perek which is an interlude, yes.
So how come at times, and I think more often than not
unless I'm wrong, the גמרא Gemara would say מה הוי עלה? Mah
havay alah? You know like all these opinions in the משנה, Mishna,
then the גמרא Gemara just doesn't even conclude anything?
Well, as I keep on telling you that גמרא Gemara is not
primarily interested in פסקנ'ינג. paskening. Every now and then, you know, there's
a פסק psak discussion, but mostly it's not. And particularly something like
this. What פסק? psak? I don't know, but particularly like this, you
know, it could be the period of you know where these are
open discussions, depend on who which רבי Rabbi you went to, which
גאון Gaon you went to, which אמורא Amora you went to until
things got a little bit, and even nowadays it depends who you
ask. Not everything, anyway. But the גמרא's Gemara's primary interest is analyzing,
is not פסקנ'ינג. paskening. And particularly here where the פסק psak is,
you know, is really primarily about a חטאת. chatas. It's not even
a question about מותר muttar or אסור. assur. Okay, now yes.
One more question. All these talks about, you know, if you're going
to carry something this size versus that size,
but
רבנן rabanan they אסור'ד assur-ed all carrying outside of an
עירוב. eruv. Right.
That's what I said, the only relevance of all of this is
either theoretically if you are have to bring a חטאת chatas offering,
right? If you when there's a בית המקדש. Beis ha-Mikdash. Or the
possible relevance is that like, you know, under some circumstances where we
allow things if it's a דרבנן de-rabanan or a double דרבנן de-rabanan
or these types of an issues, you know, even when we do
that we usually talk about things that are more removed from the
biblical act. Meaning if we talk about like, well let's say it's
the case of a sick
person. way or something of that nature. Here, or here where you
actually are doing the act itself, just quantitatively a little bit less,
that’s like the probably last דרבנן d’rabbanan that we would want to
allow because it’s like everything is in place for you to be
doing the מלאכה melacha except the quantity is a little less than
the minimum amount. So, but it is true that that would be
the one area of relevance where you really had to do something
for a serious issue like a sick person or something of that,
then it’s important to get it down to a דרבנן d’rabbanan level,
if it’s not like life-threatening and so on. But you’re right, that’s
what the point I’m making, not only is it so much effort
and time spent on carrying, but on an area which has very
little relevance. Okay, so now we have an interlude. This whole next
פרק perek is an interlude, and it is because the last משנה
mishna ended with quoting a פסוק pasuk from ישעיהו, Yeshayahu, אין ראיה
לדבר זכר לדבר, ein raya le-davar zecher le-davar, we start this פרק
perek with a דרשה drasha from the same פרק perek with from
a פסוק pasuk from the same פרק perek in ישעיהו. Yeshayahu. And
the entire משניות mishnayot in this פרק perek are devoted to הלכות
halachot that are learned out from פסוקים. psukim. Now, a lot of
הלכות halachot are learned out from פסוקים, psukim, but normally they’re learned
out normally they’re learned out from פסוקים psukim in the Torah. It
says don’t do מלאכה, melacha, it says don’t cut your פאות, peyos,
it says this, it says that, and we want to know what
are the parameters. But these are learned out from פסוקים psukim in
נ״ך, Nach, not פסוקים psukim in the Torah, and פסוקים psukim that
also maybe are not obviously talking about halachic issues but are applied
to halachic issues. And this is going to be a series of
הלכות halachot which are מנין ל... minalan le- X, where do you
know that X is the case, and then quoting a פסוק pasuk
in נ״ך Nach that is a little bit not necessarily about a
halachic point that is used for proof. And there’s a general assumption
also that these types of collections of randomly related themes but collected
from this structural way, like a good example of that would be
like
אין בין, ein bein, in the מגילה, Megillah, אין בין ein bein
this ל... le- this אלא, ela, there’s no difference between יום טוב
Yom Tov and שבת, Shabbos, there’s no difference between תפילין, tefillin, ספרים,
sefarim, תפילין, tefillin, and מזוזות mezuzos except this and so on, that
those are like early collections of משניות mishnayot when they are a
lot of different themes that they’re collected by this certain structural similarity.
Okay, now here though, although that being said, the first person to
speak here is רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
is quite late in the tannaitic period. Alright, but that’s going to
be the theme of this, there’ll be one משנה mishna later on
that does talk about a שבת Shabbos topic about ברית מילה bris
milah on שבת, Shabbos, and רש״י Rashi says that’s why it’s being
discussed this whole פרק perek is because of that משנה. mishna. תוספות
Tosafos says no, because ברית מילה bris milah is not our larger
discussion, our larger discussion is carrying, we get to ברית מילה bris
milah many, many chapters later, the only really reason this פרק perek
is here is because it connects into the quoting of the פסוק
pasuk that we did before, bringing a proof from a פסוק, pasuk,
and this starts with a similar הלכה halacha from a פסוק pasuk
from the same chapter in ישעיהו. Yeshayahu. Yes.
So, the two actually one הלכה halacha from a פסוק pasuk and
the other is, so if you quote from נ״ך Nach does it
make it only דרבנן d’rabbanan or דאורייתא d’oraisa as far as?
Well, it’s דרבנן, d’rabbanan, I mean yeah
I mean even the גמרא Gemara says אין ראיה לדבר זכר לדבר
ein raya le-davar zecher le-davar and so on. So let’s take a
look.
Okay, now most of these משניות mishnayot also, as I said, are
anonymous like the אין ביןs ein bein are anonymous. Okay, but this
it does start with a רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva but the later
ones might actually be of a much earlier vintage. But let’s start
with ours which is רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, which is the hook
to this last משנה. mishna. אמר רבי עקיבא, Amar Rabbi Akiva, said
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, מנין לעבודה זרה שמטמא במשא כנדה? minalan le-avodah
zarah she-metamei be-massa ke-niddah? How do we know עבודה זרה avodah zarah
is טמא tamei when you carry it like a נדה? niddah? A
נדה niddah is a woman who is a menstrual woman, and not
only she but also like a woman who is a זבה zavah
that has a flow, a blood flow not during a menstrual period,
or a man who is a זב zav who has a penile
emission that is not semen. They’re this category of זב, zav, זבה,
zavah, נדה niddah of people who are טמא tamei and they are
an אב הטומאה. av hatumah. They sit on something, it makes the
seat an אב הטומאה. av hatumah. If somebody carries them or carries
the seat that they sat on, then that person becomes טמא tamei
even without touching them. But here specifically, he doesn’t focus on that
whole group of people but specifically the נדה niddah because of the
פסוק pasuk will relate to a נדה. niddah. Now עבודה זרה avodah
zarah in the Torah, it never says that עבודה זרה avodah zarah
is טמא, tamei, right? It says עבודה זרה avodah zarah is forbidden
in benefit, it says you have to destroy it, it never says
it’s טמא. tamei. So this whole idea that there’s this thing of
טומאת עבודה זרה, tumat avodah zarah, ritual impurity, is basically as we’ll
see, but we can presume it’s a rabbinic idea. And now the
question is how far does it go, how much do we treat
it as rabbinically impure? So if you touch it you’re impure, let’s
say you don’t touch it, let’s say you just carry it. So
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is going to base this on a פסוק
pasuk in נ״ך, Nach, but again presumably this is not only is
the derivation rabbinic, but the whole category we will see might well
be rabbinic. So מנין לעבודה זרה שמטמא במשא, minalan le-avodah zarah she-metamei
be-massa, how do you know עבודה זרה avodah zarah is causes טומאה
tumah just by carrying it even without touching it, כנדה ke-niddah like
a נדה, niddah, שנאמר she-ne'emar as the פסוק pasuk says, תזרם כנדה.
tizrem ke-niddah.
Scatter them, these idols, like a דוה, dhavah, which is a flow,
like a woman with a flow, a menstruous woman. צא תאמר לו,
tzei tomar lo, get out, say to it, the idol. So that's
the פסוק pasuk and it's from later in that פרק perek in
ישעיהו. Yeshayahu. מה נידה מטמא במשא, mah niddah metameh b'masa, so it
compares these idols to a נידה, niddah, the same way a נידה
niddah causes טומאה tumah by carrying, אף עבודה זרה מטמא במשא, af
avodah zarah metameh b'masa, even עבודה זרה avodah zarah causes טומאה tumah
by carrying. Now obviously, you know, this is I'm waiting for Rivka
or Sari or Zahavy's comment on this.
The word דוה. dhavah. Right. Is the word that... דוה, dhavah, the
flow.
Yeah. אשה דוה, ishah dhavah, it's the same
פסוק pasuk
used in the, it's the same פסוק pasuk used in the תורה
Torah for a נידה. niddah. No, but what I thought the response
would be is that in the תורה, Torah, you look at the
general question about attitude towards נידה. niddah. You know, in the תורה,
Torah, the תורה Torah has a woman who's a נידה niddah as
טמאה, temeah, as it does a זבה, zavah, as it does a
זב, zav, and there's no particular, you know, taboo around נידה niddah
as something that is particularly like, you know, to be distanced from.
You know, it's טומאה tumah like anything else is טומאה. tumah. But
in later in נ"ך, Nach, you do have it. Like we say...
Right, right. טומאתה בשוליה, tumatah b'shuleha, you have it, you say it,
we say it in תחנון. Tachnun. What do we say, you know,
כטומאת הנידה רחקתנו, k'tumat haniddah richaktanu, which is a פסוק, pasuk, right?
So the sense that נידה niddah is not just טמא tamei like
anything else is טמא, tamei, but there's this sense of, you know,
these menstrual taboos and distance and so on, you know, you do
find echoes of that in נ"ך Nach and or explicit statements of
that. You know, the רמב"ן Ramban says clearly that was widespread in
the ancient world, not, you know, not just amongst the Jews. The
רמב"ן Ramban says, you know, when רחל Rachel says to לבן, Lavan,
לא אוכל לקום מפניך כי דרך נשים לי, lo uchal lakum mipanecha
ki derech nashim li, that what she was not saying was just
she was feeling ill, but she basically wanted to get לבן Lavan
out of the tent, and by saying that she was a נידה,
niddah, you know, because of these taboos, he would have wanted to
have given her her distance. So, you know...
Sitting on top of the camels.
I understand, I understand, but he was explaining, he was explaining why
it was an effective strategy.
So I see if idols are טמא נידה, tamei niddah, then she
would have been telling the truth.
Oh, there you go, oh, that's a good point, I didn't connect
the two. Anyway, yes, but I just want to see how the
English here reads it. Here, I'll read it to you, this is
ישעיהו ל', כ"ב. Yeshayahu lamed chaf-bet. You will contaminate the coating of
your silver graven idols and the embellishment of your golden molten images.
You will cast them away like something unclean. You will tell it,
be gone. So all they say for דוה dhavah is unclean, which
is pretty funny because דוה dhavah does mean flow. Anyway, that's at
least how...
Koren actually uses the term menstruous.
Yeah, well, I'm not surprised, that's as ArtScroll is not always so
accurate. Here, you can use this. Yes, it's okay, I trust you.
It says like a menstruant. Yeah, well, I remember when I
was in, I was in Bali in Indonesia, so a sign in
the temple says, one of the temples said, women who are menstruating
shouldn't enter. Right.
So
it's a whole other culture, very interesting, right?
Look, you have, you know, in the תורה, Torah, you have that
the, well, this gets us into a whole other conversation, but in
the תורה Torah you have, you know, that a woman after childbirth,
you know, cannot go into the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash until forty
days, right, after she's given childbirth, because she's טמאה temeah and so
on until she brings her קרבן. korban. But that, you know, but
in, and amongst certain Catholics, I believe, is it Catholics? Certain Christians,
I think Catholics, anyway, some, they basically don't, you know, women can't
come to church until forty days after childbirth. And in Ashkenazi Middle
Ages, you know, particularly in אשכנז, Ashkenaz, women who were נידות, niddas,
amongst major segments, again, not that it was הלכה, halacha, but it
was practice because of these attitudes, you know, would not be able
to go into שול, shul, or maybe some even like say ברכות
brachot or look at a ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, other types of
things. I mean, you see some echoes of this in the רמ"א.
Rema. You know, there's a question, maybe on ימים נוראים Yamim Noraim
they would be allowed, you know, or something. But anyway, so there,
but there's a lot of these issues about taboos around נידה niddah
that both, you know, in Jewish society and in other societies that
are not halachic. And I will say, and I've made this point
before, that I think the amazing thing about the גמרא, Gemara, when
it deals with הלכות נידה, Hilchot Niddah, is basically the complete absence
of this, the silence of this, meaning it doesn't even engage it
to reject it. It basically, if you read through all of מסכת
נידה, Masechet Niddah, all you get is treating it like, you know,
normal הלכה. halacha. It's טומאה, tumah, there's an איסור issur sex, there's
questions about having certain הרחקות harchakot in order, you know, but when
the גמרא Gemara discusses the distancing of husband and wife during נידה,
niddah, it compares it to, it's almost a little funny, like not
having meat and milk at the same table, is one thing going
to lead to another? You know, and so I say it's like
a little bizarre comparison, but the point is it neutralizes it. It
doesn't make it anything special. It makes it like any other הלכה.
halacha. Do you know, will one thing lead to another? Are you
concerned it'll lead to sex? Are you concerned this types of things?
So in the גמרא Gemara you would not have known this. But
it's floating out there, you know, these types of taboos. of attitudes
and they surface, so some of them surface amongst אשכנז, Ashkenaz, you
know, in אשכנז Ashkenaz and certain types of practices, and at least
here you're getting a פסוק passuk in which this attitude is reflected.
Yes.
The other thing I was going to say is sort of like
a like almost like a pun because זרם... zerem... He said זרם.
zerem.
...is to scatter, but זרם zerem is also a flow.
It could be.
It could be. And the idea of also a נדה... niddah... you
know, this question in other societies, you know, that נדות niddot would
live, you know, another amazing thing in הלכה halacha is that husband
and wife share room when the woman is נדה niddah and not
only is that a halachic חידוש chiddush that why aren't we concerned
that they'll have sex, but it's also a חידוש chiddush because of
because in so many societies the whole idea is that menstruant women
went to their own tent, went to, you know, they were dangerous
and they had a separate space. So, you know, so yes. But
the idea of נדה niddah being some say that the etymology of
נדה, niddah, like flow, also is that sense of נידוי, niddui, which
is like, you know, which is cast away, thrown out, pushed out,
and so on. So there are these issues. Yes, Rivka?
I just want to disagree a little bit with what you said
that the גמרא Gemara is neutral because there's plenty of statements in
the גמרא Gemara like someone saying women are full of filth, you
know, they're just... and גוף נקי...
guf naki... Yes, but the גמרא Gemara does not apply גוף נקי
guf naki to women. The ראשונים Rishonim do it. The ראשונים Rishonim
אשכנז... Ashkenaz...
No,
the תפילין tefillin and גוף נקי guf naki in the גמרא Gemara
is not about women. It's about men and about passing gas. It's
the ראשונים Rishonim in אשכנז, Ashkenaz, it's the ראשונים Rishonim in אשכנז
Ashkenaz who have all of those associations with נדה niddah and taboo
and all those stuff that make the association of גוף נקי guf
naki to the women issue. But the women filled with filth, that's
true, that there is that line in the גמרא, Gemara, but I
do not believe the גמרא Gemara ever, you know, sort of links
that to נדה, niddah, to the best of my knowledge.
I think it's just a general statement. But I'd have to check.
But the point is is that it is yes, but a lot
of that is associations made outside of the גמרא, Gemara, not in
the גמרא Gemara itself. One last point, Charlie, and then we'll go
on. Yes.
The Samaritans have very strict rules on נדה niddah even today. There
obviously aren't very many of them, but...
Right. And when, you know, and when the, I think Ethiopian Jewry,
right, originally, they when they are first encountered with them, we discovered
that they, you know, that the women there when they were נדה
niddah were in a separate like outside, you know, stayed in a
separate house, in a separate room, and so on. So anyway, all
right, so here we are getting a little bit of that. So,
עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. Now let's take a look at this discussion
about עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and טומאה tumah and טומאה tumah like
a נדה. niddah. So we taught over there, משנה Mishnah עבודה זרה.
Avodah Zarah. מי שהיה ביתו סמוך לעבודה זרה. Mi shehayah beito samuch
l'Avodah Zarah. Your house, actually the better גרסא girsa says כותל ביתו,
kotel beito, the wall of your house. So the wall like a
wall on your property was right near a property of a pagan
temple. ונפל, Venafal, and your wall fell down. אסור לבנותו, Assur livnoto,
you can't build it. Because you build up
your wall, you're helping create a wall for a pagan temple as
well. Since the wall serves both, so כיצד יעשה, keitzad yaaseh, what
should you do? כונס לתוך שלו ארבע אמות ובונה. Kones l'toch shelo
arba amot uvoneh.
You go into your property four אמות amot and you're building so
you're building only for your property, not on the property line which
is also building for the other עבודה זרה's Avodah Zarah property as
well. The גמרא Gemara in עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah has a problem.
If you're going four אמות amot into your property, then you're giving
some of your property over to the pagan temple. So it deals
with that issue. היה שלו ושל עבודה זרה, Hayah shelo veshel Avodah
Zarah, now let's say the place or the wall was built half
to you and half to the pagan temple. So נידון מחצה
על מחצה. niddon mechtzah al mechtzah. So you sort of divide it
half and half, which means that the half that you imagine a
line going down the middle and that half that's yours counts towards
the four אמות amot that you're moving into your property. So you
move into your property
from the inner edge of the wall, from the outer edge of
the wall, no, you imagine the property line going through the wall
and you move four אמות amot in from there.
The reason only, whatever.
אבניו ועציו ועפרו מטמאים כשרץ. Avnav v'eitzav v'afaro metammim kesheretz.
Now to the point that's relevant to us. By the way, תוספות
Tosafot has a, well, no, so the stones and the wood and
the dust of that wall are טמא tamei like a שרץ. sheretz.
So here you have עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah is טמא tamei like
a שרץ, sheretz, but what's interesting is not only the עבודה זרה,
Avodah Zarah, just a wall that was connected to an עבודה זרה,
Avodah Zarah, which is also interesting because if it's a real עבודה
זרה, Avodah Zarah, then how are you using the wall? Isn't it
אסור assur to get הנאה hanaah from things that are associated to
an עבודה זרה? Avodah Zarah? תוספות Tosafot also has another question, which
is that there's an opinion that if an עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah
breaks, even if it wasn't broken by one of its worshippers, but
if it just naturally breaks, it automatically loses its status as an
עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, because people would say, look, it can't save
itself, how is it supposed to save me? So if the wall
breaks, why doesn't that
lose any status? So the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says what we're talking about
is that after it fell down, like the worshippers worshipped even the
rocks and the dust that were on the ground. So again, it's
like a funny case because it's not really about the wall per
se, we're really not talking about. About because if it was just
a wall, why would it be considered an עבודה זרה? Avodah Zarah?
Why were you using it until now? Why would it remain אסור?
assur? So we're really talking about a different type, you know, a
different point that something that is an עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and
that was worshipped as an עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, then even in
the state of dirt and dust or whatever, it still causes טומאה
tumah
like a שרץ, sheretz, שנאמר... shenemar... Yeah, but wouldn't it be? Where
do you wait? שנאמר, shenemar, שקץ תשקצנו, shaketz teshaktzenu, you should surely
abominate it. So the word שקץ sheketz and שרץ, sheretz, abomination and
שרץ, sheretz, are very similar words, so if it's to be abominated,
you treat it like a שרץ sheretz and therefore it causes טומאה
tumah like a dead rodent, which is through contact. That's the first
opinion. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, כנדה. keniddah. No, not like
a שרץ, sheretz, like a נדה. niddah. שנאמר, shenemar, תזרם כמו דוה,
tizrem kmo davah, like the פסוק pasuk we quoted. Scatter them like
a, throw them out, cast them out like a menstruant. מה נדה
מטמאה במשא, Ma niddah metame b'massa, the same way a נדה niddah
is not just through touch but through carrying, אף עבודה זרה מטמאה
במשא. af avodah zarah metame b'massa. Even עבודה זרה avodah zarah through
carrying. So that's exactly what we have in our משנה, mishna, except
here you see it is debated. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, said
רבא. Rava. תזרם דאמר קרא, Tizrem d'amar kra, cast them away that
the verse
says. נכרינהו מינך, Nachrinehu minach, make them like זר zar from the
word זר, zar, not like זרי zarey which means to cast, but
זר, zar, foreign. Make them foreign to you, כזר, k'zar, like a
זר, zar, like a foreigner you should completely, you know, like alienate
yourself from them or them from you, distance yourself from them. צא
תאמר לו, Tzei tomar lo, get out you should say to it,
הכנס אל תאמר לו, hikanes al tomar lo, don't bring it in.
Okay, not exactly clear what רבא Rava's pointing out other than a
little דרשה drasha that תזרם tizrem is not just not just be
cast away but mean make them a זר. zar. תוספות Tosafot says
the reason of introducing that statement of רבא Rava is to explain
why even though this idea of טומאה בעבודה זרה tumah b'avodah zarah
is rabbinic, why we are choosing to interpret the verse in a
strict way and say treat it as strict like a נדה niddah
and not in a more lenient way. Okay, because of the emphasis
of this verse of so much you should push her away and
distance yourself from it. And that's going to lead רבא Rava now
to interpret the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and the Rabbis
in a in a in a more strict light that everybody is
very strict. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, said
רבא, Rava, במשא, b'massa, when it comes to carrying
an עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, דכולי עלמא לא פליגי דמטמאה. d'kulei alma
lo peligi d'metame. Everybody agrees that it causes טומאה. tumah. Not like
it sounded that the Rabbis said a שרץ sheretz and would not
be by carrying. No, by carrying everybody agrees, דמטמאה. d'metame. דאיתקיש לנדה,
De'itaish l'niddah,
it's connected to a נדה. niddah. כי פליגי, Ki peligi, when do
they debate? באבן מסמא, B'even masama, when it comes to this other
thing called the
lodestone, or not lodestone, lodestone is a magnet, right? Anyway, a weighty
stone, a very heavy stone, which is a special הלכה halakha of
נדה. niddah. I'll discuss what it is in a minute. רבי עקיבא
סבר
כנדה, Rabbi Akiva savar keniddah, it compares the עבודה זרה avodah zarah
to a נדה niddah fully like a נדה. niddah. מה נדה מטמאה
באבן מסמא, Ma niddah metame b'even masama, אף עבודה זרה מטמאה באבן
מסמא. af avodah zarah metame b'even masama. The same way a נדה
niddah creates טומאה tumah by this very weighty stone, even עבודה זרה.
avodah zarah. So it's fully like a נדה. niddah. ורבנן סברי כשרץ.
Verabbanan savri k'sheretz. No, it's like a שרץ. sheretz. מה שרץ לא
מטמא באבן מסמא, Ma sheretz lo metame b'even masama, אף עבודה זרה
לא מטמא באבן מסמא. af avodah zarah lo metame b'even masama. That
the the same way a שרץ sheretz does not, even even עבודה
זרה avodah zarah does not. So what he's saying is like this.
It sounds like since רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva emphasizes that עבודה זרה
avodah zarah is by carrying, that the debate is is עבודה זרה
avodah zarah by carrying? Either you compare it to a שרץ sheretz
and you say no, or you compare it to a נדה niddah
and you say yes. רבא Rava wants to read their debate that
everybody is strict, much, you know, stricter than we would have thought.
Everybody agrees that the פסוק pasuk is comparing an עבודה זרה avodah
zarah to a נדה niddah because it is. Everybody agrees that it
has it's טמא tame by carrying. The only debate is this very
tiny little other הלכה halakha about a נדה. niddah. This thing called
the אבן מסמא. even masama. That they're debating. That רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva says it's 100% like a נדה, niddah, even אבן מסמא. even
masama. And the רבנן Rabbanan say, "No, no, no. The fact that
the תורה Torah also compares it to a שרץ sheretz means you
don't go that far. Carrying, yes; אבן מסמא, even masama, no." Now
what is this אבן מסמא? even masama? So רש"י Rashi says, it
could be bold, רש"י Rashi says
that, you know, as I mentioned before, one of the הלכות halakhot
about a נדה niddah and a זב zav and a זבה zava
is anything they sit on becomes an אב הטומאה. av hatumah. Even
if they don't touch it. Even if you have ten cushions and
they're on the top cushion, like the Princess and the Pea, you
know, then they are because it's their seat, it's an אב הטומאה.
av hatumah. So now רש"י Rashi says, what if they don't sit
on it but it's underneath them? What if, for
example, here's a stone, it's on some
suspender, something suspended, they're sitting here and there's something underneath them, but
you know, there's a there's an air and and you know, air
between them, there's a gap. So רש"י Rashi says that's אבן מסמא.
even masama. It's something that's underneath their bottom as it were, but
they're not actually sitting on and that's a special הלכה halakha that
they also make that טמא. tame. תוספות Tosafot says that's not true.
That's not what he quotes all the דרשות. drashot. That's not what
אבן מסמא even masama is. That's a that type of טומאה tumah
does not exist. So what does it mean for תוספות? Tosafot? תוספות
Tosafot says it means you've got a huge
boulder. Now, if somebody's sitting on ten cushions, at least their body
weight is having some impact on the lower cushion. But let's say
you've got, you know, a huge boulder and a cushion underneath it...
And then somebody sits on the boulder. So obviously they're adding a
little weight, but obviously the little weight they added by sitting on
a boulder that's on top of some cushion is their sitting has
no impact on the cushion below. So that is a case where
they are that that is considered an אבן המסמא even hamasama in
the sense that even that causes טומאה, tumah, even though they are
it's not really a classic מושב moshav of a נידה niddah or
of a זב zav or whatever, it's not something that really their
weight put weight on it. Nevertheless, we learn from a special פסוק
pasuk that that's a special category of טומאה tumah as well. He
has a couple of other variations. But the point is it's not
a classic מושב moshav because it is not the weight doesn't impact
it, but on the other hand it is something that they are
sitting on, just sitting on through a huge boulder. And that's this
special category.
So and then on top of something else, but not something else
is on top of it. Like if she's sitting on a mountain
and then there's like a cushion on the bottom of it?
No, well, how you get a cushion underneath a mountain? But the
boulder, the boulder, the boulder is on top of something else. That's
the point. Yeah. Now there could be other reverse cases as well.
He says because then the question is, because nobody is suggesting by
the way that by עבודה זרה avoda zara you have this category
called called like מושב. moshav. So anyway, תוספות Tosfos says another possibility
is let's say you've got your foot underneath a boulder and you've
got something on top of the boulder. Normal משא massa is like
you're carrying the זב zav or the נידה niddah or the נידה
niddah is carrying something else. But let's say you're not really carrying,
meaning the נידה'ס niddah's underneath the boulder and something's on top of
the boulder. It's not really being carried by the נידה, niddah, it's
being carried by the or the reverse. So those are also cases
of this type of a sort where the effect of your body
as the carrier or the carree or the sitter are very is
negligible or not almost nonexistent because it's basically through a boulder. And
nevertheless, there's this category of that, the special category called אבן המסמא
even hamasama by נידה. niddah.
What should a נידה niddah sit on
in order not to cause טומאה? tumah?
Well, that if you had a special נידה niddah chair...
Well, again, if you're talking about כהנים Kohanim in which this is
a real issue that needs to be avoided, one does wonder, even
though I just got through saying that we did that you don't
have this idea of נידה niddah in a separate room and husband
and wife sharing a room even when the woman's a נידה, niddah,
but if you're כהנים Kohanim who have to be eating the תרומה
terumah and whatnot, then just even if there's not a הלכה halacha
requiring it, in all for practical purposes, you have to imagine that
anything she's
sitting on the bed so he let's say...
Right, so he sits on the bed, right, he becomes טמא, tamei,
right, so you do have to imagine the bed is the bed
is an אב הטומאה, av hatumah, right. So I know. So if
it's כהנים, Kohanim, look, for non-כהנים Kohanim it wasn't much of an
issue. But you are right, meaning that even though there's no הלכה
halacha that they have to be in a separate room and as
I said חז"ל Chazal even said that when whatever, we're not concerned
about ייחוד yichud or anything whether for these issues or for just
concern of sex. But nevertheless, for כהנים Kohanim who had to eat
תרומה terumah and had to eat קרבנות, korbanos, right, it was a
real issue because you're right, what do you do for a quarter
of the, so for a man who wants a כהן kohen who
wants to eat תרומה, terumah, any place his wife sits he has
to avoid. So there would you imagine effectively they probably did have
to keep separate for that week.
Anything she's sitting on is טמא. tamei.
How do you get it טהור? tahor? You bring it to the
מקוה. mikvah. A chair? Yeah. You would bring it to the מקוה.
mikvah.
But I'm just saying this is not a taboo.
This is just... Well, you're making an excellent point which is is
that the result of... look, the הלכה halacha is the same as
true about a זב. zav. It's not unique to a נידה. niddah.
It's not unique to menstruation. But the reality is is that נידה
niddah does occur unless people are getting pregnant very often, נידה, niddah,
which they were. But okay. But anyway, נידה niddah would occur on
a very regular basis within the household. It would not be like
a זב. zav. It was a natural thing. Right, I understand. So
that you are what you're saying is a very good point that
in the house of a כהן kohen who's eating תרומה, terumah, right,
then there would have to there would effectively have to be real
separation going on, real distancing going on just to address the טומאה
tumah issues and the likelihood that that could lead to certain taboo
attitudes is certainly quite possible. Right? But you're right, you're right, you're
right within a כהן'ס kohen's house. Right, right, within a כהן'ס kohen's
house, anything she touches or whatever is טמא tamei and I have
to eat my תרומה terumah and I have to eat whatever.
This is a major issue.
Right. For כהנים Kohanim you're absolutely correct. Yeah. I don't really know
what... yeah, you're right. You're right about that. Yeah.
Is it possible that most of the תרומה terumah was eaten in
ירושלים Yerushalayim while the כהנים Kohanim were on duty because...
Maybe, but תרומה terumah is one of the מתנות בכהונה matanos bakehunah
in the גבולין gevulin where every where the farmers are and where
the כהנים Kohanim are. Look, it would be very strange also because
then when she wasn't in נידה niddah and they were having sex,
so he would he'd become so he had the טומאה tumah of
שכבת זרע, shichvas zera, about emitting semen, and then he was טמא
tamei until and he had to wait to go to the מקוה
mikvah and he was טהור tahor until nightfall. So the exact total
amount of time and opportunities for him to eat תרומה terumah were
days when she wasn't in נידה niddah and they weren't having sex.
But I'm talking about the object. The object...
the object remains טמא tamei until it's taken to a מקוה. mikvah.
Yeah.
She's contaminating everything. It's a contamination really.
Yes, but like but that's
true... Anything you touch becomes טמא tamei whatever the טומאה tumah is,
right? But here the problem here is that it is more pervasive,
even if she doesn't directly take it and it's regular, you're right.
So the fact that there are these other elements there, you know,
and that what you're saying is that they not only, they're not
independent, they sort of emerge from or coincide with some of these
halakhic realities is true. That is true.
Compared to bad things, to detestable things.
I understand, I understand. But again that's a תנ"ך, Tenach, that's not
in the Torah.
All right, this is semen causes the bed to be טמא? tamei?
Semen is an אב הטומאה av hatumah so it would make the
bed into a ראשון. rishon. The difference is that a נדה niddah
as well as a זב zav and a זבה, zavah, but a
נדה niddah is very common, you know, makes, makes things she sits
on an אב, av, the highest form of טומאה. tumah.
Yeah, so the ראשון rishon doesn't have to go to the מקוה?
mikvah?
A ראשון rishon does have to go to the מקוה mikvah but
it's, but the טומאה tumah is much less, you know, it's the
power of it is much less. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
continues. So according to Rava, they're all debating its טומאת משא tumah
massa and the whole question is this אבן מסמא even masama which
is, you know, through a rock, which is through a huge boulder,
which is a special הלכה halakhah within נדה. niddah. Okay, so that's
what he says. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this, ורבי עקיבא למאי הלכתא איתקיש לשרץ? veRebbi Akiva lemai hilkheta itkish
lesheretz? So according to the רבנן, Rabbanan, it's connected to a שרץ
sheretz to say it doesn't go so far for this אבן מסמא
even masama הלכה. halakhah. For Rebbi Akiva, why was it connected to
the שרץ? sheretz? למשמשיה, lemeshamshaha, to tell you that the עבודה זרה
avodah zarah itself is like a נדה, niddah, but the things that
are the appurtenances to the עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, things used to
serve the עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, connected to it, adorn it, those
things are only כשרץ, kisheretz, only by touch and not by
carrying. ולרבנן למאי הלכתא איתקיש לנדה? velerabbanan lemai hilkheta itkish leniddah? And
why is it connected to נדה? niddah? So we've answered that, למשא,
lemassa, to tell you that it's not totally like a שרץ. sheretz.
They agree, according to Rava's take, that it is טמא tamei by
carrying. Okay, but it's not 100% because of this אבן מסמא even
masamas thing is held back. ולכתוב רחמנא לנבילה? velikhtov rachamana leneveilah?
So all you wanted to do was to compare it to, to
say that
it's, that it's טומאה tumah of carrying, there are other things that
are טמא tamei by carrying like a נבילה, neveilah, like a corpse
of a dead animal. אין הכי נמי. ein hakhi nami. You know
what, you're right. If it just wanted to say it was טמא
tamei by carrying, it could have made that comparison. אלא, ella, so
why does it compare to a נדה? niddah? אלא מה נדה אינה
לאיברים אף עבודה זרה אינה לאיברים. ella mah niddah einah leevarim af
avodah zarah einah leevarim.
The same way if a woman who is a נדה, niddah, it's
only, you know, as a whole person. If, God forbid, you know,
a limb would fall off, she was, and the limb would not
become, would not have טומאה tumah of a נדה. niddah. It would
have maybe טומאה tumah of אבר מן החי, eiver min hachai, but
it wouldn't have טומאה tumah of a נדה. niddah. So on עבודה
זרה avodah zarah similarly, if you, if you dismember an עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, even if it could be like re-put together, it's made
as a something to assemble and disassemble and reassemble, when it is
in its disassembled state it loses its טומאה. tumah. Okay, so that's
the comparison to נדה. niddah. So now what?
Like a relic? Like part of an עבודה... avodah... like a statue?
Yeah, so
an עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, a
statue, you mean a piece of a statue? A piece of a
statue. Right, so that's a, yeah, so it's not that it's not
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. The question is about איסור הנאה. issur hana'ah.
That gets to a question about an עבודה זרה avodah zarah that's
broke. And this is even less than breaking, this is just disassembled,
something you could reassemble. So this is specifically within the הלכה halakhah
of טומאה. tumah. Within the הלכה halakhah of טומאה tumah we're being
more lenient that only when it's whole. But you make the good
point, which is correct, that when it comes to the הנאה hana'ah
prohibition, right, that even possibly even when it's broken and disassembled, especially
if disassembled isn't even necessarily broken. So according to this, we all
agree that it's like a שרץ sheretz in that it, the comparison
to נדה niddah at least excludes the case of when it's not
whole. And maybe it excludes the, and then the question is how
far otherwise do you treat it like a נדה? niddah? According to
Rava, everybody agrees that it's by carrying and the only issue is
about this issue of אבן מסמא. even masama. But one leniency we
learn is that it has to be whole, at least for the
הלכה halakhah of the טומאה tumah of it. Now, והא דבעי רבי
חמא בר גוריא, veha deba'ei Rabbi Chama bar Gurya,
that question that Rabbi Chama bar Gurya asked, עבודה זרה ישנה לאיברים
או אינה לאיברים, avodah zarah yeshnah leevarim o einah leevarim, whether the
עבודה זרה avodah zarah when, you know, when it's disassembled, does it
still have the טומאה tumah or not? So what's the הלכה? halakhah?
I mean, why did he ask that question? תפשוט ליה מהא דלרבנן
אינה לאיברים. tifshot lei meiha delerabbanan einah leevarim. So you should be
able to learn out since we're saying from נדה niddah we learn
this principle that it doesn't apply when it is disassembled. Okay, and
so why does he still have his question? רב חמא בר גוריא
אליבא דרבי עקיבא בעי לה. Rav Chama bar Gurya aliba deRebbi Akiva
ba'ei lah. He's asking according to Rebbi Akiva, meaning Rebbi Akiva says
from נדה niddah we learn out this special category of אבן מסמא,
even masama, even this huge stone. So for him, we don't know
what the story is about the, about the disassembled. But according to
רבנן, Rabbanan, from נדה niddah they learn out this idea of being
disassembled. So again, it's a little bit confusing because it's this whole
sort of accounting about, you know, what you learn out from each
part of it. But just to review, everybody learns out from נדה
niddah that it causes טומאה tumah of carrying. Rebbi Akiva goes so
far to learn out that it's even this even... So if you
have a question whether it applies whether it's whole or not, that's
only according to רבי עקיבא, Rebbi Akiva, because the rabbis, what they
learn out from נדה Niddah is specifically this הלכה, halakha, that only
when it's whole, not when it's dismembered. That's one approach. Yes. Is
that also true of שרץ? Sheretz? I mean if the leg of
a שרץ Sheretz fell off, would it... Well, the רב Rav says
it would be if there was enough of it, yes, but it's
specific to נדה Niddah because נדה Niddah is about the person, not
about, you know, it's not a complete objectification, right? By שרץ Sheretz
it's about the object, so even in pieces, but נדה Niddah it's
only about the whole person. So that is a good, yeah, you're
right, that is unique to נדה. Niddah. Is there a minimum size
in terms of the עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah you're carrying? Yeah, we'll
get to that. רבי אליעזר אמר, Rebbi Eliezer amar, so that's רבא's
Rava approach, that everybody agrees by משא massa and the whole debate
is אבן מסמא, even mesama, what you learn from נדה Niddah אבן
מסמא even mesama or do you learn from נדה Niddah this idea
of being whole. Let's just read the next opinion, get to the
bottom of the דף. daf. רבי אליעזר אמר באבן מסמא דכולי עלמא
לא פליגי דלא מטמא. Rebbi Eliezer amar be'even mesama d'kulei alma lo
pligi delo metamei. No, no, no. You went overboard. Everybody agrees that
it's not so much like a נדה, Niddah, it does not apply
to אבן מסמא.
even mesama. They're debating the more obvious point of carrying. כי פליגי
במשא, ki pligi bemassa, they're debating carrying.
Just like it sounds like. רבי עקיבא סבר כנדה, Rebbi Akiva savar
ke'niddah, like a נדה, Niddah, מה נדה מטמא במשא אף עבודה זרה
מטמא במשא. ma niddah metamei bemassa af avodah zarah metamei bemassa. That
same way נדה Niddah is by carrying, even עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah,
that's what רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva emphasizes, by משא, massa, carrying. רבנן
סברי, Rabbanan savri, and the rabbis say, no, they emphasize the שרץ
Sheretz comparison. כשרץ, ke'sheretz, מה שרץ לא מטמא
במשא אף עבודה זרה לא מטמא במשא.
ma sheretz lo
metamei
bemassa af avodah zarah lo metamei bemassa.
So that's a much more reasonable read, that the debate is, is
it like a שרץ, Sheretz, is it like נדה, Niddah, how for
the הלכה halakha of carrying. רבי עקיבא למי הלכתא איתקש לשרץ? Rebbi
Akiva lemai hilkheta itkash lesheretz? So according to רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva
that it is by carrying, what's the point of comparing of comparing
the עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah to a שרץ? Sheretz? למשמשיה, l'meshamesheiha, for
the things that appurtenances, the עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah itself is like
a נדה, Niddah, carrying, but the appurtenances are a שרץ. Sheretz. לרבנן
למי הלכתא איתקש לנדה? l'rabbanan lemai hilkheta itkash leniddah? So if for
the rabbis it's just like a שרץ Sheretz and not carrying at
all, so what's the point of connecting to a נדה? Niddah? So,
מה נדה אינו לאיברים, ma niddah einu le'eivarim, like we said before,
not to tell you this idea that it has to be whole,
the same way a נדה Niddah doesn't apply when it is you
know, when
it's God forbid like a limb has fallen off, אף עבודה זרה
אינו לאיברים. af avodah zarah einu le'eivarim. Even עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah
is not for limbs and we will pick up with this interesting
discussion tomorrow.